Guide to the New York Juvenile Asylum records (Children's Village),
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
New York Juvenile Asylum records (Children's Village),
1853-1954
New York Juvenile Asylum.
117.5 linear feet (137 boxes: 31 document boxes, 1 half document box, 105 ledgers in custom-made boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1488
6909466
The collection is composed primarily of ledgers used in the operation of the New York Juvenile Asylum, a reception center, home, and placement agency for orphaned, abandoned, and impoverished children. The Asylum operated in Manhattan from 1853 until 1905 when it moved to a rural campus in Dobbs Ferry, New York. In 1920 the Asylum was renamed Children's Village. The collection provides copious information about the experience of poor and orphaned children, children sent West on "orphan trains," social work, and the home life and living arrangements of poor and immigrant New Yorkers in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Historical Note
The New York Juvenile Asylum (NYJA) was founded in 1851 by a group of prominent businessmen and professionals concerned about vagrancy among poor children in New York City. The Asylum was designed to house, educate, reform, and find placement for the numerous homeless and runaway boys and girls found daily on the streets of New York. The founders conceived of the Asylum as a place for non-delinquent children--an alternative to the punitive House of Refuge for young criminals. After operating in Manhattan for over half a century, the NYJA moved to Dobbs Ferry, New York, where it became a boy's school. In 1920, the institution was renamed Children's Village, and it continues to operate under this name today.
From 1854 to 1905, NYJA occupied a large building in Washington Heights on 176th Street between Tenth and Eleventh Avenues. The building was the hub of a larger social services network that extended throughout New York City and into the towns of the West. Children reached the Asylum in several ways. Many were found vagrant or committing petty theft and were delivered to the NYJA by the police. Others were removed from homes that were deemed unfit, and quite a few were surrendered by parents or relatives too poor or too incapacitated to care for children. No matter their origin, children first arrived at the House of Reception on West Thirteenth Street where they were assigned a case number. After a few days assessment at the House of Reception, staff sent appropriate cases uptown to the Juvenile Asylum, where children received six hours of schooling a day as well as moral, religious, and vocational training.
Many of these children traveled to the West (on "orphan trains") where they were indentured to farmers. The NYJA had a permanent agent stationed in Illinois to assist in placing children with families. The Asylum kept track of the children until they reached adulthood, sometimes corresponding with orphans and the families with which they were placed for years. These materials provide abundant information about the experience of "orphan train" children apprenticed to Western states.
Not all children at the NYJA were truly orphans and many were released to parents or family members after periods of financial difficulty had passed. No records exist for these children after they were reunited with families.
At the dawn of the twentieth century, as new ideas about social work spread though the United States, the building in Washington Heights began to feel cramped and outdated. In 1901, the trustees of the NYJA held an architectural design competition for a suburban facility to be built on a farm in Dobbs Ferry, twenty miles north of Manhattan. The winning design featured a cluster of residential cottages that quickly earned the nickname "Children's Village." The new facility had space for less than a third of the youth who had lived in the Manhattan asylum. Before the 1905 move, female, African-American, Jewish, and Catholic children were sent home or to other institutions. In 1920, during a reorganization that promoted a therapeutic model of care, the institution's name was officially changed to "Children's Village." Children's Village still operates as a treatment center and residential facility for boys in Dobbs Ferry, New York.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of ledgers used for record keeping at the New York Juvenile Asylum and Children's Village. The collection of ledgers, while large, is also fragmentary and represents a minority of the total volume of records NYJA produced. The majority of the ledgers document the movement of children through the asylum system, from arrival at the House of Reception to discharge to family or apprenticeship in the West. The ledgers also concern financial operations, committee minutes, and daily operations at the Asylum in Manhattan as well as the Dobbs Ferry Children's Village campus. Correspondence copybooks contain onionskin paper impressions of letters regarding institutional operations. Several of the ledgers contain papers and correspondence interleaved with the bound pages. Many are in fragile condition. A small number of reports and papers from a 1931 institutional survey are also included.
This collection is arranged in four series.
Series I: Administrative Records, 1853-1954
Series II: General Operation Records, 1853-1950
Series III: Daily Logs, 1858-1953
Series IV: Children's Village Papers, 1921-1936
Subjects
Children's Village (Dobbs Ferry, N.Y.).; New York (N.Y.)--Social conditions.; Charities--New York (N.Y.); Children--Middle West.; Children--Institutional care--New York (State); Correctional institutions--New York (State); Indentured servants--Middle West.; Juvenile detention homes--New York (State); Orphans.; Orphans and orphan asylums.; Orphan trains--United States.; Poverty--New York City.; Runaway children.; Social work.; Registers (lists).
Access Restrictions
The Medical Logs (Box 85, Folders 2-5 and Box 95, folder 1) are restricted. Researchers wishing to use the Medical Logs first must sign a nondisclosure form certifying that they will not publish, or in any way disseminate, names or personally-identifiable information from the Medical Logs. This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Transferred from Teacher's College Archives, 2006.
Selected Related Material at Other Repositories
Records of the Children's Aid Society New-York Historical Society. New York, New York.
Papers of Charles Dewey Hilles, 1902-1909 Yale University.
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1853-1954
  This series contains ledgers pertaining to the overall operation of the New York Juvenile Asylum and Children's Village. The ledgers comprise minutes, correspondence, and financial records. The minutes do not provide a complete record of institutional operation. The correspondence is recorded in copybooks on onionskin and primarily dates to the early twentieth century. The ledger of Admissions, Indentures, and Discharge correspondence contains many original letters interleaved with copies. The financial records also largely consist of copies on onionskin. The Reports of Costs to City and State list the numbers of children housed at the institution each month and were used to collect public funds from the city and state.
  - Minutes--Committees
    - Indenturing, 1853-1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Admissions, Indentures, and Discharges, 1862-1872 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Admissions, Indentures, and Discharges, 1889- 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Admissions, Indentures, and Discharges, 1920- 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Applications, House of Reception, Visiting, 1854- 1863 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Visiting, 1864-1871 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Visiting, Books, 1897- 1887 (Box 3)
    - Supply, 1879-1894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes--Board of Directors
    - 1905-1918 (volume 4) (Box 128)
    - 1918-1925 (volume 5) (Box 129)
    - 1925- 1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936- 1952 (Box 5)
    - 1953- 1954 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Indentures--Outgoing, 1868-1870 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Admissions, Indentures, and Discharge, with Invoices-- Incoming and Outgoing, 1873-1880 (Box 8)
    - Indentures--Regarding Schwartz and Billotti, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General, 1897-1903 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - General, 1903 (Box 9)
    - General, 1904- 1908 (Box 10)
    - General, 1905 March-May (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General, 1905 September-October (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - General, 1906 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - General, 1907 April-June (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - General, 1907 July-October (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - General, 1908 February-March (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - General, 1908 March-June (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - General, 1908 July-September (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - General, 1911- 1912 (Box 15)
    - General, 1914 April-August (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - General, 1917 June-December (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - General, 1919 June-November (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - General, 1920-1921 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - General, 1921-1922 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - General, 1922-1923 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - General, 1923-1924 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Financial
    - Report of Costs to City and State-- Billing
      - 1868-1870 (Cover Only) (Box 96, Folder 4)
      - 1872-1876 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - 1895-1898 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - 1898-1899 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Children Receiving Private Financial Support, 1894- 1898 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Receipts and Payments--"Cash Book", 1941-1944 (Box 21)
- Series II: General Operation Records, 1853- 1950
  The General Operation Records form the heart of this collection and pertain to the movement of children though the asylum system. Many of these records contain unique case numbers that were assigned to each child.
  The Registers of Children list the age and important characteristics of new arrivals at the House of Reception, such as race, religion, language spoken, and name and address of parents. These records reveal that NYJA housed Catholic and Jewish, as well as Protestant children, and admitted African-American and immigrant youth. Most of these registers contain case numbers and information about the eventual fate of the child: if she was sent to the Asylum, home to family, or out West as an apprentice. Some unusual cases are marked with additional notes.
  Social workers created Home Visit Records when they visited the families of children living in the Asylum to determine whether those families could provide a fit home for children. These visits were conducted for children living in the Asylum who had families with a known address. These ledgers do not all follow the same format. Some contain an Admission form and Discharge form on facing pages. A social worker filled out the first of these forms when a child was removed from his home. The facing, Discharge, form was filled out when a child returned home, sometimes years later. Where noted, some ledgers contain only Admission or only Discharge forms. In these cases, each individual page was dedicated to a single child and only contains information about the condition of that child's home, either when she was admitted to NJYA, or when she was released to her family. The ledgers provide a wealth of detail about home life and living arrangements among poor and immigrant New Yorkers in the latter half of the nineteenth century.
  Parent Surrender Forms were used when parents or family members relinquished control of their children to the institution. These are brief forms and contain little more than children's names and the names and signatures (or marks) of the parents.
  Apprentice Records kept track of older children indentured to homes in the West. The records contain information about the lives and experiences of these children and the families who took them in. Indentured children and the families who housed them reported their progress and satisfaction with placement regularly. The NYJA maintained contact with these children until they reached adulthood, and sometimes afterward, if formerly indentured children remained in contact. The Apprentice Records therefore give an excellent overview of the experience of “orphan train” children.
  Transfer Slips record where children were sent (usually to the NYJA) after arriving at the House of Reception.
  Applications for Discharge were required of all parents and guardians wishing to retrieve their children from the asylum. The forms record how fit the applicants are to care for a child and whether discharge was granted or denied. Most of the children applied for were discharged to their guardians.
  - Register of Children (Alphabetical Index with Case Numbers)
    - "NYJA Register No. 1," 1858-1888 (Box 26)
    - "NYJA Register No. 2," 1885-1923 (Box 27)
  - "Children's Village Index and Register"--Case Numbers 44827-51300 1926-1950 (Box 39)
  - Case Records, 1853- 1854 (Box 22)
  - Case Numbers 28576-37035, 1891-1902 (Box 24)
  - Case Registers--House of Reception (Box 20)
    - Case Numbers 5705-6567, 1860 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 6568-7367, 1861 January-December (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 7368-8323, 1862 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Case Numbers 8234-9658, 1863- 1864 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Case Numbers 9485-10508, 1864-1865 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 10371-12025, 1866 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 12021-12947, 1867 (Box 130, Folder 1)
    - Case Numbers 12943-13838, 1868 (Box 130, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 13797-15336, 1869-1870 (Box 130, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 15337-17035, 1871-1873 (Box 130, Folder 4)
    - Case Numbers 17036-18354, 1874-1875 (Box 131, Folder 1)
    - Case Numbers 18355-19744, 1876-1877 (Box 131, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 19745-21467, 1878-1880 (Box 131, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 21468-23520, 1881-1883 (Box 132, Folder 1)
    - Case Numbers 23521-25462, 1884-1886 (Box 132, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 25463-27543, 1887-1890 (Box 132, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 27486-28131, 1890 (Box 99)
    - Case Numbers 28132-28745, 1891 (Box 82)
    - Case Numbers 28746-29369, 1892 (Box 100)
    - Case Numbers 29370-29938, 1893 (Box 101)
    - Case Numbers 29938-30528, 1894 (Box 102)
    - Case Numbers 30538-37078, 1895 (Box 103)
    - Case Numbers 31079-31741, 1896 (Box 104)
    - Case Numbers 31771-32478, 1897 January-September (Box 105)
    - Case Numbers 32479-32686, 1897 September-December (Box 106)
    - Case Numbers 32687-33390, 1898 February-September (Box 107)
    - Case Numbers 33391-33669, 1898 September-December (Box 108)
    - Case Numbers 33670-34574, 1899 (Box 109)
    - Case Numbers 34575-35578, 1900 (Box 110)
    - Case Numbers 35579-35647, 1900 December (Box 111)
    - Case Numbers 35648-36233, 1901 January-July (Box 112)
    - Case Numbers 36234-36667, 1901 August-December (Box 113)
    - Case Numbers 36668-37264, 1902 January-July (Box 114)
    - Case Numbers 37265-37528, 1902 August-December (Box 115)
    - Case Numbers 37529-37938, 1903 January-July (Box 116)
    - Case Numbers 37939-38172, 1903 August-December (Box 117)
    - Case Numbers 38173-38677, 1904 January-August (Box 118)
    - Case Numbers 39242-39844, 1906-1909 (Box 119)
    - Case Numbers 39845-40448, 1909-1911 (Box 120)
    - Case Numbers 40449-41050, 1911-1914 (Box 121)
    - Case Numbers 41051-41652, 1914-1916 (Box 122)
    - Case Numbers 41653-42259, 1916-1918 (Box 123)
    - Case Numbers 42260-42863, 1918-1919 (Box 124)
    - Case Numbers 42864-43467, 1919-1921 (Box 125)
    - Case Numbers 43468-44063, 1921-1923 (Box 126)
    - Case Numbers 44064-44337, 1923 (Box 127)
  - "Register of Children Sent to the Asylum" (Chronological) (Box 25)
    - Case Numbers 11700s-18100s, 1867- 1875 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Case Numbers 18100s-26100s, 1875-1887 (Index without Discharges) (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Case Numbers 26130-31734, 1888-1896 (Index without Discharges) (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Case Numbers 31715-40691--"Transfers from House of Refuge to Cottages," 1897-1912 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - "Girl's Admissions and Discharge Register," 1881-1897 (Alphabetical) (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Asylum Current Register (Alphabetical Index with Case Numbers)
    - 1896- 1898 (Box 28)
    - 1898- 1901 (Box 29)
    - 1901- 1903 (Box 30)
    - 1903- 1905 (Box 31)
    - 1905- 1910 (Box 32)
    - 1911- 1914 (Box 33)
    - 1914- 1918 (Box 34)
    - 1918- 1920 (Box 35)
    - 1920- 1924 (Box 36)
    - 1924- 1925 (Box 37)
    - 1924-1940 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Home Visit Records
    - 1898- 1901 (Admissions) (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - April-June 1898 (Discharges) (Box 40)
    - 1898-1901 (Discharges) (Box 41)
    - 1898-1899 (Admissions) (Box 42)
    - 1901-1902 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 43)
    - 1901-1903 (Discharges) (Box 44)
    - 1902-1903 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 45)
    - 1903-1904 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 46)
    - 1904 (Admissions) (Box 47)
    - 1903-1905 (Discharges) (Box 48)
    - 1904-1905 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 49)
    - 1905-1907 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 50)
    - 1910-1911 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 51)
    - 1910-1912 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 52)
    - 1912-1914 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 53)
    - 1913-1915 (Admissions and discharges) (Box 54)
    - 1915-1917 (Admissions) (Box 55)
    - 1917-1918 (Admissions and Discharges) (Box 56)
    - 1918-1919 (Admissions) (Box 57)
  - Parent Surrender Forms
    - 1853- 1861 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - 1867-1870 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - 1873-1875 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - 1876-1878 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - 1878-1880 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - 1888-1891 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Apprenticeship Records
    - Index to Apprentice Register--Alphabetical (Box 65)
      - 1862- 1878 (Box 65, Folder 1)
      - 1879-1901 (Box 65, Folder 2)
      - 1902-1906 (Box 65, Folder 3)
      - circa 1900s (Box 136, Folder 1)
      - Undated, (2 volumes) (Box 136, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Indentures/Case Notes, 1854-1888 (with Case Numbers) (Box 61)
    - Indentures/Case Notes, 1888-1906 (with Case Numbers) (Box 62)
    - Indentures/Case Notes, 1868-1879 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Indentures/Case Notes, 1871-1876 (Arranged by Date and Group) (Box 63)
    - Indentures/Case Notes, 1876-1880 (Arranged by Date and Group) (Box 64)
    - "N. Y. Juvenile Asylum Agents Record," 1862-1868 (with Case Numbers) (Box 98)
    - Record of Employer and Apprentice, 1869- 1870 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Transfer Slips--House of Reception (Box 65)
    - Case Numbers 33281-3, 4139 January-June, 1899 (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Case Numbers 37251-37727, 1902- 1903 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Discharges (Box 67)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1862-1863 (Box 67)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1864-1865 (Box 68)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1865-1867 (Box 69)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1867-1869 (Box 70)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1869-1870 (Box 71)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1871-1873 (Box 72)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1873-1875 (Box 73)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1875-1877 (Box 74)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1877-1879 (Box 75)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1879-1881 (Box 76)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1881-1883 (Box 77)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1883-1885 (Box 78)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1885-1887 (Box 79)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1887-1889 (Box 80)
    - Applications for Discharge, 1889-1894 (Box 81)
    - House of Reception Discharges, 1885- 1898 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - House of Reception Discharges, 1899-1905 (Box 133)
    - Discharges, 1928-1938 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Discharges, 1939-1946 (Box 83, Folder 1)
- Series III: Daily Logs, 1858-1953
  This series contains records of daily activity in the NYJA and Children's Village, including visitor's registers, daily events, runaways, and medical and school records. They offer a fragmented but illuminating glimpse into daily operations at the institution.
  Physicians' Certificates certified that children who entered the asylum system were in good physical and mental health and free of infectious diseases. Inspecting doctors could record any health problems that were present. Almost all the children were found to be healthy and given a clean bill of health.
  The Doctor's Orders Books and Medical Logs were kept at the Children's Village infirmary. The former records medical treatments prescribed by physicians and the latter lists the complaints of children who visited the nurse each day.
  - Visitors' Logs
    - 1858- 1900 (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - 1901-1905 (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - Daily Log
    - 1899- 1902 (Box 84, Folder 2)
    - 1914-1917 (Box 84, Folder 3)
    - 1917-1921 (Box 133, Folder 2)
    - 1936-1941 (Box 133, Folder 3)
  - Log of Runaways, 1929-1935 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Children's Village "Day Book" (Admissions, Discharges, Enrollment--with Case Numbers)
    - 1925- 1933 (Box 86)
    - 1933- 1940 (Box 87)
    - 1940- 1941 (Box 88)
  - Physicians' Certificates
    - 1886-1887 (Box 89)
    - 1887- 1888 (Box 90)
    - 1888- 1889 (Box 91)
    - 1889- 1890 (Box 92)
    - 1890- 1891 (Box 93)
    - 1892- 1893 (Box 94)
    - 1893- 1894 (Box 134)
    - 1894- 1895 (Box 135)
  - "Doctor's Orders Book"
    - 1949- 1951 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - Medical Log
    - 1951- 1952 (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Treatment--Charles Jerome, 1899-1906 (Folder 5)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - School Records "Roll Books"
    - 1897- 1898 Volume 1 (Box 95, Folder 2)
    - 1897-1898 Volume 2 (Box 96, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Children's Village, 1921-1936
  The bulk of this series consists of a 1931 New York University study of Children's Village, along with papers and plans for new buildings on the campus. These documents were produced as part of an initiative to modernize the curriculum to reflect current educational and therapeutic developments. The series also contains published pamphlets and programs reporting on the progress of Children's Village in the early twentieth century
  - "Brief Survey of Children's Village," 1929, (2 Folders) (Box 96, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Minard, G. C. to Edmund Dwight, 1934 December 6 (Box 96, Folder 5)
  - New York University Studies and Reports (Box 97)
    - "First Semi-Annual Statement Concerning Educational Re-Organization at Children's Village," 1931 (Box 97, Folder 1)
    - "A Little Theatre for Children's Village," Mary Allen Tippett, 1931 (Box 97, Folder 2)
    - "Report on the Francis McMillan School of Carpentry," Hugo J. P. Vitz, 1931 (Box 97, Folder 3)
    - "Report on the Michael Friedsam School of Masonry," Hugo J. P. Vitz, 1931 (Box 97, Folder 4)
    - "Report on the Willets-Schulte Plumbing School," Hugo J. P. Vitz, 1931 (Box 97, Folder 5)
    - "Report on the Lytelton Deane Electrical School," Hugo J. P. Vitz, 1931 (Box 97, Folder 6)
    - "Prevocational Building Study," 1931 (Box 97, Folder 7)
  - "From Juvenile Asylum to Treatment Center," Peter Carr Sexias, M.A. Thesis, 1981 (Box 97, Folder 8)
  - "Open Letter from the President to the Members of the Board of Directors," 1926 September 15 (Box 97, Folder 9)
  - "Proceedings of the National Conference of Juvenile Agencies," 1936 September (Box 97, Folder 10)
  - School of Printing Motto, Undated (Box 97, Folder 11)
  - "School Program for the Problem Child," 1932 (Box 97, Folder 12)
  - "Second Annual Report," 1932 August 31 (Box 97, Folder 13)
  - "Seventieth Annual Report"--Pamphlet, 1921 (Box 97, Folder 14)
  - "Third Annual Report and Second School Bulletin," 1933 (Box 97, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising Correspondence--Scrapbook 1929 (Box 137)